True to its name, only Oracle
seemed to see this coming.
Oracle is having its
biggest jump since 1992.
What a blowout quarter
for the software company.
Maybe the stock of the year.
And then just days later...
TikTok's US operations is
said to be acquired by a
consortium including Oracle.
Oracle shares spike
after its named as part
of the consortium.
What was going on?
This was an old-school enterprise tech
firm tickling investors
in places only a flashy
startup normally reaches.
Because Oracle basically said that
they have almost half a
trillion dollars of contracts
to be earned in the next few years.
And that was a shocker.
Everyone was modeling
maybe, you know, $150 billion.
It blew away analyst expectations.
Now, Oracle's deeply connected to one
of the hottest social media
properties on the planet
and behind one
of the most ambitious infrastructure
projects on the planet.
Oracle had been written off
as a kind of IBM-like company.
This is an incredible comeback story.
Clearly we had an
amazing start to the year -
This, is Safra Catz.
Safra Catz is the CEO
and she's considered by
Wall Street to be one
of just the sharpest financial
minds out there, right?
I mean, investors love her.
Never more so than on September
9th when she stunned Wall
Street with Oracle's quarterly earnings.
They showed a spike in
bookings at a scale which nobody
had ever really seen before.
At the end of its fiscal first quarter,
Oracle's $455 billion
forecast was a fourfold
increase over the same
period a year earlier.
Infrastructure revenue alone will grow 77%
to $18 billion this fiscal year.
So yeah, it was a good day
to be Oracle co-founder Larry Ellison,
whose net worth soared by
$89 billion as a result,
almost enough to buy
Starbucks or four Lululemons
or half a Qualcomm.
That was the biggest one
day gain ever recorded on the
Bloomberg Billionaires Index.
He must have been very pleased.
You know, online commentators
were saying, okay,
it's never too old to grow, right?
He is a 81-year-old,
and briefly, he is the
world's richest man.
He started 2025 in fourth place.
It was only in July that
he passed Mark Zuckerberg
to move into second place, even though him
and Elon Musk are vying for first place.
Ellison is also a major
investor in Musk's company.
I'm very close friends with Elon Musk
and I'm a big investor in Tesla.
Musk quickly regained the title,
but that this happened at
all was a sign the world had
wildly underestimated old-timer Oracle.
Several things converged
to give Oracle the leg up
of a lifetime, and we're going
to explain what they are.
But first, it's worth a quick
recap of Oracle's origin story
and what it is the company actually makes.
Larry Ellison founded
Oracle in 1977, just a year
after the emergence of Apple,
and two years after Microsoft.
In fact, he started working
in a government job at the
CIA, and that's how he
got the idea for Oracle.
It was a crowded decade on
Silicon Valley's maternity ward
with engineers in bell bottom
jeans delivering startup
after startup to the sound of prog rock.
Although, if possible,
Ellison wasn't listening
to anything quite as fun.
He wanted to help businesses
organize their private
data more efficiently.
Oracle really pioneered
the modern database.
In the early computer age,
just heaps of information
were being created.
There needed to be a mechanism
to keep track of all that.
Oracle's database was one
of the great cash cow
businesses of all time,
And by 2025, Oracle's
customers included some
of the world's best known
companies from AT&T to Walmart,
Accenture, and Volkswagen.
Their vast databases, years,
if not decades in the making,
think of them like the
biggest, most sensitive
and important folders of
spreadsheets ever known
to humankind.
They're traditionally stored in
what are called on-premises environments,
basically on servers in the offices
or facilities of the
companies who own them.
This helps ensure privacy and compliance.
A lot of these big
companies started using Oracle
databases back in the
seventies or eighties
and have never stopped.
Alright, back to the present day.
What did investors
think Oracle's plan is?
One is to sell inference AI
models to existing clients.
The other one is to basically
sell cloud computing
capabilities or data centers.
The traditional leaders here,
Amazon, Microsoft, Google,
they're strained for capacity.
And so Oracle figured, God,
we got all this cash flow,
we're printing billions off
of our other businesses.
We're able to use that
to underwrite our growth into
the cloud infrastructure.
But the plan surpassed
external expectations.
Here's how much Wall Street
thought Oracle's infrastructure
as a service business would generate over
the next few years.
But this is what Oracle
says it now expects.
Some of these buyers
like OpenAI have committed
to almost $300 billion in compute
that they want Oracle to
provide them over the course
of multiple years.
Its deals like that
that have really prompted this investor
enthusiasm around Oracle.
A lot of investors
and analysts are assuming that
if it can do deals like that,
there will be more coming down the line.
In August, Nvidia CEO
Jensen Huang said he expected
as much as $4 trillion to be
spent on AI infrastructure
by the end of the decade.
Which brings us to Project Stargate.
A lot of folks started paying attention
to Oracle this year when they
appeared at the White House,
next to Sam Altman, next to the president
announcing this Project
Stargate, this kind
of ambitious goal to
invest hundreds of billions
of dollars in AI infrastructure.
I think this will be the most
important project of this era.
Project Stargate is a
multi-year investment.
It's a partnership between
Oracle, OpenAI and SoftBank
and the goal is to build data
centers for AI across the US.
OpenAI and Oracle have
agreed to a cloud contract,
which is probably the single
largest contract in history
to build out these massive
data centers across the US.
Ground has already been
broken here in Abilene, Texas,
but it's just the first and
its capacity is off the scale.
Oracle and OpenAI have
agreed to about four
and a half gigawatts of computing power.
That's about two Hoover Dams.
That's about four nuclear reactors, right?
I mean, this is a sum of electricity
that has never really been
considered for data centers.
And so we come to another reason.
Investors are taking a
fresh look at Oracle.
You look even better now.
Thank you, Mr. President.
He seems to have
developed a pretty close
relationship with the president.
Having that close
proximity to the president
it's a big positive.
Particularly when it comes to deals
and issues of national security.
We have to backtrack till
2020 when President Trump was
trying to ban TikTok, worrying
about it being a national
security risk, and TikTok went to Oracle
and said, hey, we need to
expand our infrastructure.
Oracle right now pretty
much runs the whole
of TikTok US assets,
and they've been doing that
over the past two plus years.
And when it comes to divesting
from the Chinese parent
company, when it comes to
getting your data in a format
that's gonna appease lawmakers,
Oracle has had a big part of this
And it's what led to this.
Bloomberg understands that Oracle
and Silver Lake are among the companies
that will acquire TikTok's US operations.
US operations would
be controlled by a group
that you know, you've come
to know pretty well in Silicon
Valley-
I feel like we'll be in
the retirement home one day
analyzing this.
Well, if we are, at least
it'll now be grounded in a
better understanding of
the reason for excitement
around Oracle's blow-up numbers.
But let's be real, investments
and commitments of these scales,
the risks are huge.
Among all the hyperscaler providers,
Oracle is the most leveraged
and is bleeding the most cash.
Oracle, one of the world's
great cash cow businesses has
gone negative free cash
flow on this build out.
CEO Safra Katz said
that CapEx was gonna be 9
billion higher than expected,
and investors were excited.
And the reason for that is
that the sooner they put the CapEx in,
the sooner they get these data centers up
and running, the sooner
they can recognize revenue
from all these customers.
When you look at the
$300 billion contract
with OpenAI, there are two questions.
Question number one is
whether Oracle has the money,
put all the capital expenditure in
to buy all the Nvidia chips
and lease out the data centers so
that it can service OpenAI.
On the other hand, does OpenAI have the
$300 billion to shell out?
OpenAI has committed
to giving Oracle more money
than it has in revenue today.
It's assuming that the
current growth rates continue,
and so if anything goes wrong
there, this is a serious risk
for Oracle.